

# Fuda van Diggelen

### PhD candidate,

Artificial Intelligence: Evolutionary Robotics

17-09-1993

Beukenhof 42, Lelystad

🗾 +31 6 188 28 127

fuda.van.diggelen@vu.nl

Netherlands

### Online Presence -

Personal website

Google Scholar profile

in LinkedIn profile

Github
YouTube

## Languages

■ Dutch

■ English

■ Python

■ C++

**₩** MATLAB

## Hard Skills -

Mathematics, ML/Control Theory

Robotics, Gazebo, ROS, openCV

Machine Learning, Deep learning, Online-learning, Self-modelling

Data analysis, Statistical modeling

# Soft Skills -

Creative Thinking

Communication

Writing

Problem Solving

### **About Me**

As a 4<sup>th</sup> year PhD candidate in evolutionary robotics, I have developed a deep interest in the fields of embodied intelligence, complex systems, and control theory. With dual masters in Human Movement Science and Mechanical Engineering, I can bring a unique perspective by combining techniques from different fields to tackle challenging projects. My research focuses on the integration of machine learning with bio-inspired control for robots in unknown environments. Here I developed model agnostic controllers for complex adaptive systems, using data-driven modeling. My main interest lies in self-adaptive control systems.

## **Working Experience**

2020 – Now PhD Candidate VU Amsterdam, Computer Sciences Artificial Intelligence: Evolutionary Robotics

2024 – 2024 **Visiting Researcher** École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) Research on generative design of tensegrity robots

2022 – 2022 **Visiting Researcher** Technology Innovation Institute (TII)
Autonomous drone swarm experiments using CrazieFly platform

2019 – 2020 **Research Internship** VU Amsterdam, *Computer Sciences* Conducting evolutionary robotics research for my master thesis.

2018 – 2018 **Teacher Assistant** VU Amsterdam, *Behavioural and Movement Sciences* Teaching during practicals in the course Physics and Measurements.

#### **Education**

2020 – 2024 PhD. Computer Science, Artificial Intelligence
 Ph.D. thesis is not published yet.

 2018 – 2020 MSc. & ME. Mechanical Engineering, Biorobotics
 Focus: Analysis and application of bio-inspired design for robotic systems.

2017 – 2020 MSc. Human Movement Science: Research cum laude VU Amsterdam Focus: Understanding neuromechanical perception-action coupling through sensorimotor feedback control.

2014 – 2017 **BSc. Bewegingswetenschappen** VU Amsterdam Focus: Bio-physics on human movement and control.

### Scientific Outreach

- Youtube: A video repository on past projects and published papers [link].
- **Rijksmuseum Boerhaave**, **brAInpower**: Temporary exhibition of our lab work in national science museum [link].
- **De kennis van nu special**, *de robot evolutie*: Dutch national television documentary featuring my PhD work [link].
- Joint Lectures on Evolutionary Algorithms (JoLEA): Presented in a lecture series on evolutionary algorithm [link].

### **Besides Work**

Relaxing Sports, reading books and meeting with friends.
Sports Climbing/bouldering, football, and running.

Music Writing congs, playing the guitar and going to fo

Music Writing songs, playing the guitar and going to festivals.

Gardening Growing a vegetable garden.

## **Other Activities, Projects & Achievements**

- Extracurricular Courses:
  - 2024 Causality (UVA)
  - 2023 Winterschool on Efficient Deep Learning (ASCI);

Machine Learning Theory (UVA)

- 2022 IEEE RAS on Multi Robot Systems (CTU)
- 2021 Evolutionary Computing (VU); Deep Learning (VU)
- 2020 Data Mining Technique(VU); Learning Machines (VU)
- Research Visit, EPFL: Building autonated design pipeline for tensegrity soft robots, at École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL).
- Research Visit, TII Abu Dhabi: Developing Computer Vision based Model-Predictive control in racing drones (at ICRA) and lead researcher in swarm robotics experiments, at Technology Innovation Institute (TII) Abu Dhabi.
- **Nominated for best Master thesis award:** at Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam for my work *The Role of Proprioceptive Feedback in Learning*.
- 2nd Place in ICAR drone competition: Autonomous drone flight competition.
- **3rd Place in MRS competition:** Summer school competition on multi-robot collaboration with drones where I developed a novel planning and control algorithm.
- Master Programme Committee: Representing students' interest and advising programme board.
- **Volunteering during COVID-19:** Helped build the *Dutch ICU Data Sharing* pipeline, and developed reinforcement- and supervised- learning models to improve hospital policies.
- Rotterdam marathon: Completed the Rotterdam marathon in 3:24:55.

### References

#### prof. dr. Guszti Eiben

VU Amsterdam, Computer Science

a.e.eiben@vu.nl

**Relationship:** Guszti Eiben is head of the Computational Intelligence group at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, and my main supervisor during my PhD.

#### dr. ir. Eliseo Ferrante

VU Amsterdam, Computer Science

e.ferrante@vu.nl

**Relationship:** Eliseo Ferrante is an assistant professor at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, and my daily supervisor during my PhD.

# **Publications**

2024	A model-free method to learn multiple skills in modular robots  F. van Diggelen, N.P.A Cambier, E. Ferrante, A.E. Eiben  Nature Communications 15(1), pp. 6267.  doi: 10.1038/s41467-024-50131-4
2024	Emergence of specialized collective behaviors in evolving heterogeneous swarms <i>F. van Diggelen, E. Ferrante, A.E. Eiben</i> Parallel Problem Solving from Nature (PPSN XVIII), LNCS 15149, pp. 53-69 doi: 10.1007/978-3-031-70068-2_4
2023	Comparing robot controller optimization methods on evolvable morphologies <i>F. van Diggelen, E. Ferrante, A.E. Eiben</i> Evolutionary Computation. pp. 1-19 doi: 10.1162/evco_a_00334
2022	Predicting responders to prone positioning in mechanically ventilated patients with COVID-19 using machine learning  T.A. Dam, L.F. Roggeveen, F. van Diggelen, et al.  Annals Intensive Care 12(1). pp 1-9  doi: 10.1186/s13613-022-01070-0
2022	Environment induced emergence of collective behaviour in evolving swarms with limited sensing  F. van Diggelen, T. Karagüzel, J. Lo, E. Ferrante, N. Cambier, A.E. Eiben  In Proceedings of the Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference. pp. 31-39  doi: 10.1145/3512290.3528735
2021	The Influence of Robot Traits and Evolutionary Dynamics on the Reality Gap F. van Diggelen, E. Ferrante, N. Harrak, J. Lo, D. Zeeuwe, A.E. Eiben IEEE Transactions on Cognitive and Developmental Systems doi: 10.1109/TCDS.2021.3112236
2021	Large-scale ICU data sharing for global collaboration: the first 1633 critically ill COVID-19 patients in the Dutch Data Warehouse L.M. Fleuren, M. Tonutti, D.P de Bruin, et al. Intensive care medicine 47(4). pp. 478–481 doi: 10.1007/s00134-021-06361-x
2021	Comparing lifetime learning methods for morphologically evolving robots <i>F. van Diggelen</i> , <i>E. Ferrante</i> , <i>A.E. Eiben</i> In Proceedings of the Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference Companion pp. 93-94 doi: 10.1145/3449726.3459530
2021	Risk factors for adverse outcomes during mechanical ventilation of 1152 COVID-19 patients: a multicenter machine learning study with highly granular data from the Dutch Data Warehouse  L.M. Fleuren, M. Tonutti, D.P de Bruin, et al.  Intensive care medicine experimental, 9(1). pp. 32  doi: 10.1186/s40635-021-00397-5
2021	Learning Directed Locomotion in Modular Robots with Evolvable Morphologies G. Lan, M. De Carlo, F. van Diggelen, J. M. Tomczak, D. M. Roijers, and A.E. Eiben Applied Soft Computing, 111. pp. 107688 doi: 10.1016/j.asoc.2021.107688
2020	The Effects of Adaptive Control on Learning Directed Locomotion <i>F. van Diggelen</i> , <i>R. Babuska</i> , <i>and A.E. Eiben</i> IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence (SSCI). pp. 2117-2124 doi: 10.1109/SSCI47803.2020.9308557